A Finding Aid to the Joe Lopez Papers and Gallista Gallery Records, 1966-2016, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Joe Lopez papers and Gallista Gallery records
1966-2016
Archives of American Art
Lopez, Joe, 1945-
AAA.lopejoe
Archival Resource Key
1.7 Linear feet
32.93 Gigabytes
The Joe Lopez papers and Gallista Gallery records measure 1.7 linear feet and 32.93 GB and date from 1966 to 2016. The collection is comprised of biographical records that include interviews with Lopez, autobiographical writings by Lopez and writings by others, printed and digital materials, artwork, and photographic and moving image materials. Records for the Gallista Gallery include trademark files and legal records pertaining to the lawsuit against Lopez by E and J Gallo Winery over the use of the word "gallo."
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Joe Lopez papers and Gallista Gallery records were donated by Joe Lopez in 2016.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C., Research Center. Use of archival audiovisual recordings and born-digital records with no duplicate copies requires advance notice.
Biographical / Historical
Joe Lopez (1945- ) is a painter and founder of the Gallista Gallery (1996-2016) in San Antonio, Texas.
Lopez grew up in El Barrio Escondido, a neighborhood in San Antonio. He was introduced to art through his Uncle Basilio, a folk artist. While a student at St. Anthony Shrine School, Lopez gained the attention of one of the nuns which led to a scholarship to attend the Witte Museum Art School. He also attended La Villita School of Art, the San Antonio School of Art, and was awarded a scholarship to McNay Art Museum school. Lopez trained with artists Warren Hunter, John Squire Adams, Finis Collins, and Jesus "Chista" Cantu. Because Lopez was born with one hand, artist Jesse Treviño was an inspiration to Lopez for his ability to paint with one hand.
Lopez's paintings often feature gallos, the Spanish word for roosters, because they symbolize strength and pride in Chicano and Mexican American culture. Lopez opened his own gallery in 1996 because he was having difficulty booking exhibitions at other galleries. The original name of the gallery was Puro Gallo, and he changed the name to Gallista Gallery in 1998. Gallista was coined by Lopez to describe those who supported him during a five year court battle with E and J Gallo Winery. The wine company initiated the lawsuit against Lopez over the use of the word "gallo." The gallery became a bedrock of the community, fostering the talents of local Latino artists long after the lawsuit ended.
Early in his career, Lopez worked in the art department for Dillard's and Centeno's supermarket before becoming employed in the graphics department at Fort Sam Houston, a U.S. Army post in San Antonio. He retired in 2007 from Fort Sam Houston after 22 years.
Lopez's work has been exhibited at the McNay Art Museum, Laguna Gloria Art Museum, and other museums throughout Texas. His paintings have been featured on posters and covers of music albums including Taquachito Nights: Conjunto Music from South Texas produced by Smithsonian Folkways Recordings and Puro Gallo by Los Padrinos.
Scope and Contents
The Joe Lopez papers and Gallista Gallery records measure 1.7 linear feet and 32.93 GB and date from 1966 to 2016. The collection is comprised of biographical records that include interviews with Lopez, autobiographical writings by Lopez and writings by others, printed and digital materials, artwork, and photographic and moving image materials. Records for the Gallista Gallery include trademark files and legal records pertaining to the lawsuit against Lopez by E and J Gallo Winery over the use of the word "gallo."
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as six series.
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1966-2013 (Boxes 1, 3; 6 folders, ER01-ER06; 19.32 GB)
Series 2: Writings, circa 1997-2002 (Box 1; 6 folders)
Series 3: Gallista Gallery Records, 1990-2016 (Boxes 1, 3; 0.8 linear feet, ER07; 7.53 GB)
Series 4: Printed Materials, circa 1975-2015 (Boxes 1-3; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 5: Artwork, circa 1990-2008 (Boxes 2-3; 5 folders)
Series 6: Photographic and Moving Image Materials, circa 1985-circa 2010 (Box 2; 0.2 linear feet, ER08-10; 6.10 GB)
Painters -- Texas -- San Antonio; Interviews; Scrapbooks; Latino and Latin American artists; Mexican American artists; Chicano art movement; Art galleries, Commercial -- Texas; Gallista Gallery
- Biographical Materials, 1966-2013; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 5 Folders Boxes 1, 3; 22.6 Gigabytes ER01-ER06
  Scope and Contents
  Biographical materials include numerous awards and certificates received by Lopez for his work with the U.S. Army and arts related organizations and events, material for his first solo exhibition at the Mission Gallery, and documents relating to his marriage ceremony in 1966. The series also includes Lopez's interviews in digital format and via e-mail correspondence with a college student and Los Inocentes, as well as an interview with Gary Keller about Lopez conducted by Manuel Martinez.
  - Awards and Certificates, 1983-2013; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Includes a photograph of Lopez receiving a Certificate of Promotion from the Department of the Army.
  - Awards and Certificates, 1996-2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Ford Salute to Education Luncheon, San Antonio, TX, Digital Video Recording, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key; 3.28 Gigabytes One computer file; Partial recordings only (Folder ER10)
    Fourth and fifth videos in the recording.
  - Citation Ceremony, City of San Antonio (June 23, 2005), Digital Video Recording, Archival Resource Key; 10.94 Gigabytes One computer file (Folder ER01)
  - Hispanic Heritage Month Event, U.S. Medical Command, Fort Sam Houston, TX (September 18, 2007), Digital Photographs, Archival Resource Key; 0.246 Gigabytes 52 computer files (Folder ER02)
  - Retirement Luncheon, San Antonio, TX (December 13, 2007), Digital Photographs, Archival Resource Key; 0.023 Gigabytes Nine computer files (Folder ER03)
  - Exhibition, Hermosa Vida, Mission Gallery, circa 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
    File contains an exhibition announcement, clipping, and price list for Lopez's first solo exhibition.
  - Interview, Gary Keller Interviewed by Manuel Martinez, 2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Interview was conducted via e-mail regarding Lopez.
  - Hispanics Today, TV Program; Interview, Digital Video Recording, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key; 6.42 Gigabytes One computer file; Partial recordings only (Folder ER04)
  - KLRN TV, Interview, Digital Video Recording, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key; 3.28 Gigabytes One computer file (Folder ER10)
  - Paintings of Joe Lopez, student video for the RTV Department of San Antonio College (April 4, 2002), Digital Video Recording, Archival Resource Key; 1.63 Gigabytes One computer file; Partial recording only (Folder ER05)
  - The Artist Speaks: Exploring Who I am - Franco Mondini Ruiz, Joe Lopez & Terry Ybanez (April 25, 2012), produced by UTSA, The Academy for Teacher Excellence, Digital Video Recording, Archival Resource Key; 0.059 Gigabytes One computer file; Partial recording only (Folder ER06)
  - Wedding Documents, 1966; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Writings, circa 1997-2002; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 6 Folders Box 1
  Writings consist of Lopez's collection of autobiographical short stories and a radio commercial script. Other writings are by Irma I. Rodriguez, a play by Christopher St. John Sampayo, Xavier Garza, and poems by various authors often about Lopez and the Gallista Gallery.
  - By Lopez, "Corazon de Gallo: Non-Fiction Short Stories", circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Includes handwritten manuscripts and printed copy.
  - By Lopez, Radio Commercial Script, circa 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - By Others, "American Education Project: Survival of Education in Three Generations of Mexican-Americans," Student Paper by Irma I. Rodriguez, 2002; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - By Others, "The Gallista," Play by Christopher St. John Sampayo, circa 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - By Others, Poems, circa 1995-2003; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Includes poems, mostly about Lopez, by Nephtalí De León, Reyes Escalante, Jesse G. Herrera,and Citlali Zentella.
  - By Others, "Puro Gallo" by Xavier Garza, circa 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Gallista Gallery Records, 1990-2016; Series 3; Archival Resource Key; 0.8 Linear feet Boxes 1, 3; 7.53 Gigabytes ER07
  This series contains building records; contracts and agreements; a mix of personal and business correspondence; a fundraising event held early in the gallery's history; press; projects that include files for Arizona State University, Canto del Gallo, and Los Padrinos music album cover art; promotional materials; files mostly relating to the lawsuit against Lopez by E and J Gallo Winery; a scrapbook of printed materials and photographs; and files for the trademark of the Gallista Gallery logo.
  - Building, Certificate, 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Building, Lease, 1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Building, Sales Flyers, circa 2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Building, Survey Plat Drawing, 1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Survey is for Gallista Gallery location at 1913 S. Flores Street.
  - Contracts and Agreements, 1994-2014; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1990-2016; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
    The majority of the correspondence is regarding Lopez's business activities, but is also with friends, family, community members, artists Richard Sanchez and Jose Esquivel, former State Rep. Jim Solis, staff members at the Serie Project, and with supporters of Lopez during the lawsuit with E and J Gallo Winery.
  - Logo Design, circa 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Press, circa 1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Press, circa 1999; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Projects, 1998-2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19-22)
    Includes publishing and other projects with Arizona State University, and a sound recording of Puro Gallo by Los Padrinos. Commercially published recording not transferred.
  - Round Table Discussion, Gallista Gallery (September 27, 2008), Digital Video Recording, Archival Resource Key; 7.53 Gigabytes One computer file (Folder ER07)
  - Projects, 2009; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Promotional Material, 2006; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Puro Gallo, circa 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24-28)
    The majority of the materials are legal papers regarding the lawsuit against Lopez by E and J Gallo Winery and include files for law firms, the Puro Gallo Defense Fund, and the gallery's lease.
  - Scrapbook, circa 2000s; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 3)
    The scrapbook contains exhibition announcements and other printed material produced for Gallista Gallery along with photographs of events and people associated with the gallery.
  - Trademark, 1994-2013; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29-36)
    Includes trademark reports and U.S. Patent Office files for the trademark of Gallista gallery products.
- Printed Materials, circa 1975-2015; Series 4; Archival Resource Key; 0.4 Linear feet Boxes 1-3
  Printed materials contain art reproductions, booklets and pamphlets, Lopez's first business card, clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, flyers, magazines, newsletters, and posters relating to Lopez, his career, and Gallista Gallery.
  - Art Reproductions, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Art Reproductions, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Booklets and Pamphlets, 1989-circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Business Card, Lopez's First Business Card, circa 1985; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Clippings, circa 1988-circa 2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Clippings, circa 1988-circa 2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, circa 1980-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Flyers, circa 1990-2015; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Magazines, 1999-2014; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
    Includes several issues of Los Inocentes Not Guilty in which Lopez is credited as the art editor.
  - Newsletters, 2001; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Posters, circa 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Artwork, circa 1990-2008; Series 5; Archival Resource Key; 5 Folders Boxes 2-3
  Artwork consists of drawings, mock-ups, and sketches by Lopez and unidentified artists. Some of the preparatory drawings and sketches are labeled with the final artwork's title. Mock-ups include sketches with text for flyers and other projects, as well as a print on fabric.
  - Drawings, circa 1990-2008; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Mock-Ups, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Mock-Ups, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Sketches, circa 1990-circa 2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Sketches, circa 1990-circa 2005; Archival Resource Key (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
- Photographic and Moving Image Materials, circa 1985-circa 2010; Series 6; Archival Resource Key; 0.2 Linear feet Box 2; 6.1 Gigabytes ER08-ER10
  Photographic and moving image materials of Lopez are photographs, digital prints, and in digital format; photographs of events; photographs and a digital print of the Gallista Gallery; and photographs and slides of works of art.
  - Joe Lopez, circa 1990-circa 2010; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Includes photographs and digital prints, many labeled, of Lopez and others at exhibitions and other events.
  - Joe Lopez, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - King Huevo Joe Lopez and Queen Huevo Enedina Vasquez, Huevos Rancheros Gala and Art Auction (October 16, 2004), Digital Photographs, Archival Resource Key; 0.27 Gigabytes 121 computer files (Folder ER08)
  - El Barrio on My Mind, Mural with students, Digital Video Recording, circa 2000; Archival Resource Key; 3.28 Gigabytes One computer file; Partial recording only (Folder ER10)
    Second video in recording.
  - Events, circa 1990s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Images en Transicion, The Evolution of Contemporary Imagery in El Dia de los Muertos, Institute of Texan Cultures, University of Texas at San Antonio, Digital Video Recording, circa 1995; Archival Resource Key; 2.55 Gigabytes One computer file (Folder ER09)
  - Day of the Dead in Corpus Christi, TX, Alamo Telecommunications Council, Digital Video Recording, circa 1995-2005; Archival Resource Key; 3.28 Gigabytes One computer file (Folder ER10)
    Third video in recording.
  - Gallista Gallery, circa 1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Works of Art, circa 1985-circa 2000; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13-14)